What peoples are related to the Hungarians by
Какие родственные народы венграм по
language, we, we don't know this, Liang
языку мы мы этого не знаем Лян это
describes this, we know, look, the Khanty and Mansi are the
описывает знаем смотри Ханты и манси
closest, the Khanty and Mansi are
ближайшие Ханты и манси они
genetic, look
генетические яы Посмотрите сейчас вот
right now, if you don't believe me,
прямо сейчас если вы не верите Я
look right now, uh, the Hungarian language and its
Посмотрите сейчас ээ венгерский язык и
related languages, the Khanty, the Khanty and
его родственные языки Ханты Ханты и
Mansi are the closest by language, this is a
манси по языку самые близкие это
related language, where are
родственный язык
you from, from Siberia, and more specifically, from
Вы откуда из Сибири А конкретнее из
Tyumen, I understood, you are communicating with the World Cup, you are talking about
Тюмени понял ЧМ общаетесь
different things, you are talking about Slavic studies now, you are a
О разном сейчас о славистики говорили вы
Slavist, no, I am just a whistle by education, well,
славист нет я просто по образованию
I was talking about
свист ну я там рассказывал про
birch bark letters, about all sorts of things, yes,
берестяные грамоты про всякое такое Да
this is exactly my profile, what
это как раз мой профиль что у вас
interests you, therefore, what about Lenten letters, you know, well, I
интересует поэтому Что постным грамотам
know that they were found in
знаете Ну знаю что их найдено в
Novgorod, four in Moscow, and three in Lvov,
Новгороде в Москве четыре и во Львове
super, and look, this is your
три супер да ещё смотрите это у вас
data for what year, and three were also found in
данные за какой год А ещё найдено на
Karelian, recent data, there
карельском три недавние данные буквально
is literally a register of letters and they all
есть реестр е ны грамот и все
register, and they were found in Belarus, too,
прописывают да и в Беларуси найдено тоже
not only in Belarus, so look, they
не не только в Беларуси значит смотрите
were found in Moldova, in
найдено в Молдове в
the city of Beltsy, they were found in
городе Бельцы найдено в
Mogilev-Podolsky in Ukraine This is a complete
могилёв-подольский в Украине Это полный
full register because I just
полный реестр потому что я как раз по
defended my dissertation on birch bark letters
берестяна грамотам защищал диссертацию
Yes, in Belarus there are some in the Gomel
Да вот в Белоруссии есть в Гомельской
region there are some in Brest there are some in Kobrin and
области есть в Бресте есть в Кобрине и
I think in Pinsk I ca
по-моему в Пинске вот насчёт Пинска
n't say for sure about Pinsk right now Yes, there are some on the Kola
точно сейчас не скажу да на Кольском
Peninsula and yes,
полуострове есть и да на Кольском
one was found on the Kola Peninsula Yes, only in
полуострове найдена одна Да только на
my opinion in the 10th century Yes, and there are still Well, now
по-моему века Да и есть ещ Ну сейчас идт
we are arguing about whistles or is it
спор у нас ди свистов или она
authentic or is it later Well, let's say
аутентичная или это позже ну скажем
later later a late fake in the
позже позднее поздней подделка в
Astrakhan region was found
Астраханской области была найдена в
last year Yes, but Yes, but now it has
прошлом году Да но Да но сейчас её в
not been included in the register because well, as if
реестр не внесли потому что ну как бы
for us the area of ​​birch bark letters is the
для нас Ареал берестяных грамот
Astrakhan region and it is not clear whether it was
Астраханская область и непонятно либо
brought there with merchants somewhere,
это с купцами где-то завезена была туда
yes, or this or this is a late fake,
да либо это либо это подделка поздняя
someone for himself, like, because there was a fashion in the
кто-то себе типа потому что мода была в
10th century for these birch bark letters also
X веке на эти берестяные грамоты также
Yes, and now they are researching Well, in my opinion, they
Да вот и сейчас исследуют ну по-моему в
found them in the 10th century No, weren't the first ones found Well,
X веке нашли нет разве первых не ну
look  in the 10th century Yes, in the 10th century, there were different
смотрите в X веке Да в X веке разные там
counts of defense, they were interested in
графья обороны им было интересно разную
collecting different antiques and making
старину коллекционировать и делать
replicas of copies of antiques That's right, no, it's exactly
реплики копии старины Вот и так нет
that the first insane literacy was found in the
именно что первую бесю грамоту нашли в
20th century. It's correct But this found thing, yes, we are
20 ве прально Но вот это найденное да мы
now establishing either it is authentic
сейчас устанавливает или это аутентично
or it is
или или это
just a kind of forgery of the 10th
просто как бы подделка X
century, cool I see And so what else are you
века круто Понятно А так вы что ещё ти
studying,
изучаете
therefore Yes, I talked to your
поэтому Да всякое тут беседовал с вашими
historical bloggers, they don't
блогерами историческими оними слово
let me put in a word and they turn you off, they disconnect, and I
вставлять не дают и вырубают отключаются
understood everything And they run away Well, I'm not a blogger But
и всё понял И убегают Ну я не блогер Но
I, it's true, ran away from me when I
я итас от меня сбежал когда ему
told him that there is
рассказал что есть
Oleg in the Cambridge document that
Олег в кембриджском документе что там он
this Oleg is confirmed there Well, yes, in the
подтверждается этот Олег Ну да в
Cambridge document, he kept saying
кембриджском докумен он всё рассказывал
that it's all mythical,
что это всё мифическая
I'll explain why you look at this
обн я объясню почему так смотрите этот
You probably have this ktis, he adheres to
Вы наверное этот ктис он придерживается
the theory that Oleg is a mythical character and there is
теории что Олег мифический персонаж и
nothing further than Igor, yes, but he
дальше Игоря ничего нету да но он
relies only on
опирается только на
these European continental works Yes,
континентальные эти труды да
indeed, there is a recollection of Oleg in Oxford,
действительно в Оксфорд есть вспоминание
but there is a discussion in the scientific community
Олега но в учёной среде идёт дискуссий
Yes
Да принимать
whether to accept this Oleg as that Oleg or
ли как бы этого Олега за того Олега или
not while I am inclined to
не принимать пока я склоняюсь что
accept I am inclined to say that yes it was that
принимать я склоняюсь что да это был тот
Oleg but the majority of scientists do
Олег но большинство большинство учёных
not recognize him as that Oleg Well there is
не признаёт его как того Олега Ну там же
another Arabic source I think
ещё один есть источник арабский по-моему
some kind of Peaches where the same Oleg is
какой-то персики где тот же Олег
mentioned Well I honestly don't
упоминается Ну я честно говоря не
remember Arabic Oleg could not be mentioned
пом арабских Олег не мог упоминаться
because in Arabic the pronunciation of these
потому что в арабских произношение этих
names could not be the same as ours
имн вообще не могло быть такое как у нас
so we don't take Arabic into
так что арабский мы вообще не берём в
account at all I wonder Well I read something like there is such a thing
счёт интересно ну я что-то читал такое
he is mentioned I
что как бы есть такое упоминается он
think in the campaign against when the Rus attacked The point is that it
по-моему в походе на когда Русы напали
all started with Rurik the
на Суть в том что всё началось с Рюрика
most important thing is that the founder of
самое основное что ВС родоначальник
everything was Rurik Yes Rurik who by
всего был Рюрик Да Рюрик он кто по
nationality was a
национальности был
Swede Leons Bernese analogues it is written
Швед леоны бернских аналогах написано
that they are dreams he is a Swede that is a Varangian The Varangians
что они сны он Швед то есть Варяг Варяги
were Swedes yes that is in fact all
- это шведы были да то есть по сути все
these territories are Swedish territories
эти территории - это шведские территории
illegally occupied by Russia there
незаконно оккупированные Россией вот там
Novgorod Ladoga And so on  Yes, Jesus was killed by
Новгород Ладога И так дальше Да исус
pestilence and all this was also written about this,
дали мором и всё это тоже было об этом
it rightfully belongs to the Swedes,
пишут это по праву принадлежит шведам
therefore, Charlemagne Yes, when at
поэтому Карл Великий Да когда под
Poltava he came to take back his own Peter
полтавой он же пришёл забирать своё Пётр
I, he was essentially like the Horde, you could
I он был по сути как бы ордынцев можно
say there were no RDN, as there were none, there were no
сказать не было рдн как не было не было
RDN, so there were none, look, the Russian
рдн так не было смотрите Российская
Empire, the Heir to the Moscow State, wait, don’t
империя Наследник Московского подождите
interrupt the Moscow State Yes, and the
не перебивайте Московского государства
Moscow State is the
Да а Московское государство есть
heir to the Golden
наследником Золотой
Horde, now I can tell you to the
Орды теперь можно я расскажу до
end, there is such a traveler, Julian of
конца есть такой путешественник Юлиан
Hungary, he traveled around Russia in the 18th century, so he
венгерский он в веке путешествовал по
just described it, he was in
России вот он как раз описал он был в
Suzdal, Ryazan, Rus', so he just
Суздали Рязань Русь вот он как раз
said about the Homeland of the Hungarians, these are the Hungarians, these are the
сказал про Родину венгров это венгры это
Finno-Ugrians, he just described the Invasion of
фино Угры он как раз описал Нашествие
these very Mongols on Rus', that is, how
этих самых монголов на Русь То есть как
they attacked Suzdal, Ryazan, and so on and
они напали на Суздаль на Рязань и так
so forth, So I don’t
далее и тому подобное Так что я не
know Julian of Hungary, yes, O He wrote just
зна Юлиан венгерский да О Писал как раз
about
о
Elsa in Hungarian, where is the
Эльзе по-венгерски где
time of his transition from the Urals through the
время своего перехода из зауралья через
Carpathian Mountains under  under the leadership of
карпатские горы под предводительством
Prince Arpad yes and yes Arpad yes yes And there you
арпада князя да и да арпада да да И там
see there he just describes you
вот смотрите там как раз он описывает вы
you read you read it in what language
вы читали вы читали его на каком языке
you I read it in Latin and read it on the
вы Я читал его на на латыне и читал на
website of the Hungarian library using
сайте венгерской библиотеки с помощью
Google translator he just searched he
Google переводчика он как раз искал он
found these by the way Hungarians whom he
нашёл этих кстати венгров которых он
called Hungarians but did not create n in
называл венграми но не создали нев
Ryazan he went a little further so here Yes the
Рязани он чуть дальше пошёл так вот Да
thing is that he just described Yes
дело в том что он как раз описывал Да
that the population of these territories they are not
что население этих территорий они не
Slavs that is to say there is no such thing he just
славяне то есть су этого нет он как раз
wrote he just and I wrote on Look
писал он как раз а я писал по Посмотрите
Well I am a historian I am a historian yade he wrote this also
Ну я историк я историк яде он это писал
in going to the Volga he also has a work
в хождение на Волгу у него же есть труд
khozh no such thing there they only
хож нету там такого там только
mention that the Rus Rus are mentioned
упоминаются что Русы Русы упоминаются
Mard that
мард
is look if you now take go in
значит смотри если вы сейчас возьмёте
one I can Nani one not a single
зайдёте один пере могу Нани один ни один
translator from Hungarian will give you
переводчик вам с венгерского не даст
the word Mordva because it is a modern
слова Мордва потому что это современное
word a modern word then it is
слово современное слово тогда это
called then it was called Erz and Moksha Erz and Moksha
называе тогда это назывались эрз и мокша
Mon Moxi yes There is one But the
эрз и мокша Мон Мокси да Такой есть Но
funniest thing Look Why is Mard Why is
самое смешное Вот смотрите Почему мард
Mard this Mard You know why
почему мард это мард знаете почему
because Rubruk refers to this In
потому что на это же ссылается рубрук
his journey he describes how two
своём путешествии он описывает как два
princes went somewhere In short the
князя пошли там куда-то короче пришли
Tatars came and took these In short two princes
татары и взяли этих короче двух князей
they went there This is exactly what you decide Purga
они пошли там это как раз вот реши Пурга
Mordvin
мордовские
princes here one stayed there the other went
князья вот один там остался другой пошёл
and Julian of Hungary describes the same situation
и эту же ситуацию описывает Юлиан
in relation to those whom he
венгерский в отношении тех кого он
calls these same No The thing is that also
называет этими самыми Нет дело в том что
look also This is this Mustafa
ещё смотрите ещё также Вот этот Мустафа
Hasansky Yes an Arab historian who Well
Хасанский Да арабский историк который Ну
how did he write in Arabic but he himself was a
как он на арабском писал но сам он был
Persian he was a Persian from Khorasan This is the
персом он был персом из хорасана Вот это
modern territory of Tajikistan and
современная территория Таджикистана и
Iran it is now divided and he also walked He walked
Ирана она сейчас разделена и он тоже
almost to Novgorod he reached Yes but then
до почти до Новгорода дошёл Да но потом
he returned because of certain reasons he
он вернулся из-за определённых ще он
also described the Suzdal Principality there
описывал тоже там Суздальское княжество
And so on Yes he clearly described Yes
И так дальше Да он чётко описывал Да
that these people in their language in their way of
что эти люди по своему языку по своему
life and so on they differ from
быту и так дальше они отличаются от
people from
людей из
Pontic live around the Black Sea of ​​those
Понтийское живут вкруг Чёрного моря тех
Slavs Here they clearly indicate that there
славян Вот они чётко обозначают что там
live not Slavs, that is, the Suzdal
живут не славяне то есть Суздальское
principality is still not a Slavic
княжество это всё же не славянские
principality there were Slavs there Nadya was not
княжества были там славян Надя не было
good good and ibn Rust ibn Fadlan
хорошо хорошо а ибн Руст ибн фадлан
who describes the Slavs on the Volga this is
который описывает славян на Волге это
how to deal with this the Slavs were on the Volga since the
как с этим быть славяне на Волге были со
time of Prince Svyatoslav because Prince
времён князя Святослава потому что князь
Svyatoslav is a brave prince of Kiev Yes he
Святослав хоробрый князь Киевский Да он
defeated the Khazars, these are their Sarkel
разгромил Хазар э ихние эти э саркел
white tower Yes and their Itil were two
белую вежу Да и итиль ихние были два
large cities they were just on the Volga
больших города они были как раз на Волге
because Itil is the Volga
потому что итиль - это и есть Волга
Itil Idel Itil Yes Itil yes yes I
итиль Идель Ита итиль Да итиль да да я
know and the Slavs colonized the
знаю и славя славяне колонизировали
Kyiv Slavs with the squad prince for
киевские славяне с дружина княз за
Svyatoslav they had uh collected tribute from
Святослава они имели ээ собирали дань с
those territories they did not live there
тех территорий они там не жили там жили
different other peoples lived there and if you
разные другие народы и если Вы
look even in Derbent Well  Derbent you
посмотрите даже в Дербенте Ну Дербент вы
know the oldest city in Russia now
знаете самый старый город России сейчас
here in Derbent in the 10th century there was an
вот в в Дербенте в 10 веке было
embassy of Prince Svyatoslav because
посольство князя Святослава потому что
he he Derbent did not conquer but the
он он Дербент не завоёвывал но э
adjacent territories of the Khazar
сопредельные территории хазарского
Khaganate were subordinated to Prince Svyatoslav
каганата были подчинены князю святославу
in there was his
в было его
embassy this is a modern embassy
посольство это современному посольству
this is a battle representation yes yes Okay
это сеча представительство да да Хорошо
what to do with the deed of the Hungarians How to be
как быть с деянием венгров Как быть
Thomas Split what to do with the rhymed
фомой сплитский как быть с рифмованные
Livonian chronicle what to do with the plan
ливонским хроника как быть с плана
Carpini which clearly writes that Suzdal
карпини которы пишет чётко что Суздали
Rus and in two places look also in
Русь причём в двух местах смотрите ещ в
Berlin anals what is divided
берлинских анала тоже чт разделяется
NSH Ana Nothing is written about this it is written
нсх Ана Про это ничего не написано
that there
написано написано что там
if Bernese anals Yes everything is written no what for which for
если бернские аналы Да всё пишется нет
which locale is seen is
то что за акой за акой локали зру ется
not Rus it is definitely you just you
не Русь это однозначно вы просто вы
somewhere fragment who you are by education
где-то фрагмента вы кто по образованию
In general a programmer I have been doing this for a
Вообще программист Я этим занимался
very long time I was looking for
очень долго Я искал в иностранных
texts in Latin in foreign libraries
библиотеках на латыне тексты
with gole it is
с помою
very simple What  means
gole очень просто Что означает
in Slavic
по-славянски
Suzdal created as they think the same What does it
Суздаль создал как считают эти самые Что
mean created as this city created like
значит создал как это город создал вот
this created like this created Well look at the
так создал вот так создал Ну смотрите
Slavic cities What are they called
славянские города Как называются
Novgorod Yes for example
Новгород Да например
Terebovlya dorozhchin yes Ugu Kagarlyk
Теребовля дорогочин да Угу Кагарлык
korly not dwarf - it's a bit
корлы не карлык - это немножко
tyurt
тюр т
but there are no Slavs living in Kagarlyk not
но там не славяне живут в кагарлыке не
Kagarlyk - it's in the Kyiv region yes
Кагарлык - это в Киевской области да
now but this word has a Turkic origin
сейчас но тюркское происхождение имеет
yes
это слово да потому
because I'll explain because the Kyiv princes the
что объясню потому что у киевских князей
Kyiv princes were served by the Polovtsians and
у киевских князей служили половцы и
other Turks Berendeys some served
другие тюрки берендеи некоторые служили
Torks served Yes here su if we
торки служили Да вот су если мы
look there on the
посмотрим там на
territory just su Rostov Sursky
территории как раз су Ростова Сурских
these principalities there was such a city Golich
этих княжеств был такой город голич
nasty was Yes that's why it's called
мерзкий был Да вот почему он называется
Galich
Галич
nasty Well because once upon a time laymen lived there
мерзкий Ну потому что там когда-то жили
most likely laymen Yes Merya is
миряне скорее всего миряне Да меря - это
not a Slavic Ethnos that is to say that there were no Slavs living there just
не Славянский Этнос то есть там жили не
like cities lived Slav just like a
славяне вот также как городы жили Слав
city  Murom Why was it called
так же как город Муром Почему назывался
Murom Well because there lived Murom
Муром Ну потому что там Мурома жила
tribe Murom yes that is in all in
племя Мурома да то есть во все в
Kagarlyk Slavs lived look in
кагарлыке славяне жили смотрите в
Kagarlyk Kagarlyk - it was a settlement of
Кагарлык Кагарлык - это было поселение
Polovtsians who lived Sluzhi Prima Prima
половцев которые жили Служи
ko szhi sanzhary
Прима Прима ко сжи
sanzhary This is Slavic Yes
санжары санжары Это Славянская Да
Slavic name
славянское название
nazha where you hang out
нажа куда зависаешь
very interesting
очень интересно
initially called Sary
первоначально назвали Сары
Yary In some transcription it was
Яры В некоторой транскрипции оно в
called in Polish sanju that is Yar -
польской санджу называлось то есть Яр -
this is yarilo
это ярила
sun you you to me you to me tell me tell me
солнце ты ты мне ты мне скажи скажи
when in general Slavs when Slavs
когда вообще славяне когда славяне
got to the territory settled here lived there
попали на территорию засели вот жили там
Merya a huge number of these Merya
меря огромное количество этих меря
Murom Mordvins all sorts Yes
Мурома Мордва всякие Да
gu when a lot of Slavs got there
гу когда туда попало очень много славян
that Slavs lived there now everyone who
что там жили славяне сейчас все кто там
lives there is just about Slavs
живут это просто о славяни
furs That is the same me who taught the
фуры То есть те самые ме которы научили
Slavic language like Bulgars they are Turks
славянскому языку как Болгар они тюрки
Yes themselves but About
Да сами но О
Slavs I understood you will not
славяни я понял вы меня не будете
interrupt me I well me lie down literally for a
перебивать я ну меня леч буквально на
minute ok
минуту хорошо
Try the first  Livonian rhymed
Попробуйте первое ливонские рифмованные
chronicles they say that the Russians from
хроники они говорят о том что русские из
Pskov Pskov Novgorod and therefore Suzdal
Пскова Пскова Новгорода и значит Суздаля
they went there to fight with these and
они значит пошли там воевать с этими и
their prince Alexander By the way this is the 10th century the
князь их Александра Кстати это X век
second moment means look you
второй момент значит смотрите вы
say there that we are all Finno-Ugrians here but
говорите там что мы тут все фино Угры но
if you look at the population censuses in the
если смотреть переписи населения в
Russian Federation Well and in Russia as a
Российской Федерации Ну и в России в
whole as a whole so here are the Finno-Ugric
целом целиком так вот фино угорские
peoples such as the Karelians Mard and so on
народы такие как карелы мард и так далее
and so forth it first Well that is
и тому подобное оно сначала Ну то есть
when more or less censuses began to take
когда более-менее переписи чётки стали
place from the 1700s approximately
происходить с 1700 годов приблизительно
they grew 10 times in number and
они выросли в 10 раз в численности и
only by the 1960s they began to
только к 1960 годам они стали
decline in population means look I
сокращаться в населени значит смотрите
explain There is such a thing As
объясняю Есть такое Есть такая штука Как
mathematical
математическая
extrapolation now I explain I as
экстраполяция теперь я объясняю я как
extrapolation You can extrapolate
экстраполяция Вы можете экстраполировать
backwards you can extrapolate forward
назад можете экстраполировать вперёд
Now look What is extrapolation
Теперь смотрите Что такое экстраполяция
you you take the moment of the census when the
вы вы берёте момент переписи когда росло
population grew then the population of all
население тогда росло население всех
peoples grew because production
народов потому что производственные
capacity and the scientific and technological revolution
мощности и научно-техническая революция
Yes gave  the ability for more
Да давала возможность большему
people to eat Yes and therefore
количеству людей кушать Да и поэтому
more to survive and
большему количеству выживать и
reproduce also the same if you
размножаться так же самое если вы
take those populations of other territories
возьмёте тех населения других территорий
they all grew in numbers during
они все так само выросли в количестве в
this period explain to me Where did
этот период объясните мне Куда делось
all the population of the Volga Oka Interfluve
всё население Волга окского Междуречья
Finno-Ugric Merya go Mordvins Murom where did
фино угорская меря Мордва Мурома куда
they go so I'm talking about this
они подевались так Я же про это и говорю
that extrapolations if now there are
что экстраполяции если сейчас мордвы там
only a million Mordvins there or that
всего миллион ило того
You can just as well roll
Вы точно так же можете откатить эту
back this extrapolation and see how many of
экстраполяции назад и посмотреть сколько
them were there so there were about 50,000 of them
их там было так вот их было около 50 000
look no your methodological
смотрите нет ваша методологическая
error is that Yes in the fact that look a
ошибка в том Да в том что смотрите
huge number of modern Mordvins
огромное количество современной морд
Mordvins are recorded as Russians because in the
мордвы записано как русские потому что в
Soviet Union a huge number of
Советском Союзе огромное количество
people were recorded as Russians Yes
людей записывались Как русские Да у нас
in Ukraine people also recorded as
в Украине также люди записывались Как
Russians
русские
now I don't talk to anyone on chatroulette you are
сейчас я с кем не говорю в чатрулет ты
Russian I say where are you from from Izhevsk
кто русский говорю ты откуда с Ижевска
So maybe an Udmurt yes I am an Udmurt but like I
Так может и удмурт да я удмурт но типа я
already consider myself Russian that's all they
уже считаю себя русским вот и всё они
are not they Look  They are
быва не они Смотрите Они
Russified Mordvins Russified
русифицированная Мордва русифицированные
Udmurts And so on, yes, that is, if we
удмурты И так дальше да то есть если мы
take the so-called Russians Yes, this is
возьмём так называемых русских Да это
simply about Slavic Finno-Ugrians are different
просто о славяни ие фино Угры это разные
Merya Mordvins Murom Who
меря Мордва Мурома Которые из Киева
brought a letter from Kiev Slavic Yes, because well,
принесли письмо Славянское Да потому что
the letter came to these territories from
ну письмо же пришло на эти территории из
Kyiv Yeah,
Киева Угу
Uski monks, yes
уски монахи да
They went preachers to those territories
Они ехали проповедника на те территории
taught literacy just like the
учили грамоте также также как сейчас
Buryats now, the Buryats in Buryatia, they have
буряты вот буряты в Бурятии они уже
almost forgotten the Buryat language Yes, and they speak
бурятский язык почти забыли Да и говорят
Russian, that is, the Buryats in 50 years it
по-русски то есть бурят чере 50 лет он
will be just you will see that this
будет просто вы будете видеть что это
Burt will speak like a Russian
бурт будет говори как русский
in those territories they are also sa these are
на тех территориях они также са это те
like Buryats they already speak
как буряты они уже разговаривают на
Russian, a Slavic
русском языке славянином
language, there is one big problem with your theory The
языке тери вашей теории есть один
fact is that
большой пробле проблема Дело в том что
Julian the Hungarian he was looking for these Hungarians
Юлиан венгерский он искал этих венгров
he was looking for them by language they when he came
он искал их по языку они когда он пришёл
and this is the 10th century onir
а это X век онир
so it turns out that by the 10th century they
так вот получается что к X веку из
created all the Finno-Ogres from cutting  disappeared those
резания создали все фино огры исчезли те
who understood Ilian Hungarian Tell me
кто понимал Илиана венгерского Скажите
what peoples are related to the Hungarians by
какие родственные народы венграм по
language we we do not know this description I do not
языку мы мы этого не знаем это описва не
know look Khanty and Mansi are the closest
знаю смотри Ханты и манси ближайшие
Khanty and Mansi they are
Ханты и манси они
genetically Look right now right
генетически Посмотрите сейчас вот прямо
now if you do not believe I Look
сейчас если вы не верите Я Посмотрите
right now the Hungarian language and its related
сейчас венгерский язык и его родственные
languages ​​Khanty Khanty and Manti by language are the
языки Ханты Ханты и манти по языку самые
closest these are related language right now
близкие это родственные язык вот сейчас
we are taking no Yes no they are ethnic
мы прямо берём нет Да нет они этнические
as if by origin they are close no no
как бы происхождением они близки нет нет
now language Well their language You see what the
сечас язык Ну язык у них Понимаете в чём
thing is that the Hungarians they have a lot of words
дело в том что венгры у них очень много
in the word in the language of Turkish words
в слове слов в языке турецких слов ещё
three more times
раз три
means and others Finno Ugrians there Finns Estonians
значит и другие фино Угры там фины эсты
Yes they will not understand Hungarians at all here the
Да они венгров не поймут вообще вот
closest to Finno to the Hungarian language is
ближайший к фино к венгерскому языку это
Khanty and Khanty and Mansi So now we will
Ханты и Ханты и манси Так сейчас мы
look like this Well maybe Yes well only not
посмотрим так Ну возможно Да ну только
only not Khanty and Mansi It would be very
не только не Ханта и манси Это очень
far Why is that where they
далеко было бы Почему так они же оттуда
came from well can you imagine how long it would take
и пришли ну вы представляете сколько бы
him to walk these Hande ma rather  all these
он шёл этих ханде ма скорее всего это
were some Udmurts not not Udmurt
какие-то удмурты были не не удмуртский
at all does not look like and the second problem is what
вообще не похож на и вторая проблема в
I say that look So let's
чём я же говорю что смотрите Так давайте
we Khan
мы Хан
let's what we with the Hungarian language
давайте что мы с венгерским языком
Because it
Потому что его не
could not su the second problem of your theory and
могли су вторая проблема вашей теории и
nowhere the second problem of your theory is
нигде вторая проблема вашей теории в том
that in Mordovia itself the number of Mordvins is
что в самой Мордовии численность мордвы
growing look then I take the
растёт вот смотрите значит ээ беру
Khanty language yes Uralic family Finno-
хантыйский язык да Уральская семья фино
Ugric branch Ugric under branch
угорская ветвь угорская под ветвь
Ugric under branch Yes Well that's understandable
угорская под ветвь Да вот Ну это понятно
Yes if they Gene
Да если они Гене
in the Ugric subdivision do not interrupt me in the
в угорскую подве не перебивайте меня в
Ugric subdivision include Hungarian language
угорскую подвед входят венгерский язык
yes Khanty language and Mansi This is
да хантыйский язык и Мансийский Это
definitely because we studied it at the
точно зна потому что мы это в
university
университете изучали У нас сейчас
Of course they have diverged with us now Because if they have
конечно они разошли Потому что если они
not lived for 000 years already
000 лет не живут уже
adjacent linguistic transformation
сопредельных трансформация языковая
diverges Yes but no let's say there
расходится Да но никаких скажем там
Udmurts no Mard could not understand
удмурты никакие мард не могли понимать
these Hungarians from the word
ээ этих венгров от слова
at all we do not know this that's the
вообще мы этого не знаем вот в том-то и
problem we do not know this  we know which of them
проблема мы этого не знаем кто из них
understood zn Lin there is also Linguistic
понимал зна Лин ещё есть Лингвистический
Yes
Да
uh Mordvin language and this Uh how is it
ээ Мордовский язык и этот Ээ как он
Ugric yes that is Hungarian Yes they
э угорский да то есть венгерский Да
diverged much earlier than 1,000 years
разошлись намного раньше чем 1.000 лет
ago therefore
назад поэтому
even in the time of Julian the Hungarian they
ещё во времена Юлиана венгерского они
were already such different branches it is like for
уже были настолько разные ветви это как
example a Ukrainian would understand a Spaniard there
например украинец бы понимал там испанца
and both are
и тот и тот
Indo-European Well yes well you don't understand
индоевропейский Ну да ну не понимаете
it was exactly almost 1,000 years ago
это было как раз почти 1.000 лет назад
how many Well that's a century well I see I
сколько Ну вот век ну хоро я смот Я
just discovered yes Ugric languages ​​Because
прямо открыл да угорские языки Потому
I'm not a linguist but we went through it Yes
что я не лингвист но мы это проходили Да
at the university our specialization is
в университете же наша специализация вот
Ugric languages ​​Voskhod K Ugric formed
угорские языки Восход К угорское формиро
at the end of the millennium BC
в конце тысячелетия до нашей эры
as a result of the split of the Finno Gorsky
вследствие распада фино Горского про
language into two branches that is 3000 years ago
языка на две ветви то есть 3000 лет наза
BC that is 5000 years already it
до нашей эры то есть 5000 лет уже он
diverged from Mordvin Finnish And so
разошёлся с мордовским финскими И так
on therefore there is not even any criticism here
дальше поэтому тут даже никакой критики
we Understand what the problem is we say
мы Понимаете в чём проблема мы сказать
ourselves Hungarians they came from Siberia Topole
сами венгры они пришли из Сибири Тополе
not from  Siberia is 800 years old, look, when
не из Сибири 800 лет вот смотрите когда
they passed by, they passed by Kyiv,
они проходили они проходили мимо Киева
probably in the 10th century, in my opinion. Yes, when
наверно в веке в де по-моему Да когда
they walked there on licks, these same ones,
там они шли лижами эти самы
so it’s 800 years old. What happened to the Hungarian
так вот 800 лет что было с венгерским
language? And what happened to
языком И что 800 лет назад было с
some Udmurt language 800 years ago, we can’t
каким-нибудь удмуртским языком мы
say at all, we can, so I do
сказать не можем вообще можем поэтому я
n’t argue, but this is your desire,
не спорю но это Ваше желание
just like we can’t if Julian of
просто как не можем если Юлиан
Hungary Well, he wrote directly If you have what
венгерский Ну прям писал Если вы имеете
Julian of Hungary wrote, look,
написанный юлианом венгерским так смотри
he wrote, it was written at that time, he
он писал он же был письменный в то время
wrote in Latin, he was the Pope’s Envoy,
он писал на латыне он же Посланник Папы
he was the Pope’s Envoy, we don’t
он Посланник Папы Римского был мы не
know what he wrote there. The Hungarians already had their
знаем что он там писал у у венгров уже
own written language,
была своя письменность
then Well, it was natural, there would be
то Ну была естественно это бы
written sources, everything is accurate
е письменные источники есть всё точно
So there’s nothing here. This is your
Так что тут ничего это уже Это ваши
conjecture that they understood him there. And they
домыслы что там его понимали И так
couldn’t go on like that. No, he writes exactly about this,
дальше не могли Нет он именно об этом
that they understood him. Find it, find it for
пишет что что его понимали Найдите
me now, dictate it to me. Let
найдите мне сейчас продиктуйте Вот давай
me even find it for you now, now I will  I'll go in I
я вам даже сейчас найду сейчас я зайду я
can even read my channel in its entirety
даже могу целиком прочитать мой канал
I'll only read it to you in translation
я вам в переводе только буду читать
because it might be no no
потому что это может быть нет нет как
just in the original in the original Well we are
раз в оригинале в оригинале Ну мы
educated it's not in the original it's a translation
образова это не в оригинале это перевод
from a Hungarian
с венгерского
site so Read in Hungarian why do
сайта так Прочитайте на венгерском
I
меня зачем мне это
need this so now I'll find here
надор так сейчас я найду вот
Onan it turns out so so so so no
Онан получается
it's not that not that not
так так так так так нет это не то не то
where I recorded here
не то куда я записал вот
[music]
[музыка]
it's Harvard no no that not Here it is
оно харвард не не то не Вот она
Linus so now I'll have to look for it for a long time
линус так я сейчас ещё долго искать это
where will I
буду где буде
read it like this Well I can
читать так Ну вот я могу
pra ro stop PP stop stop stop stop stop
пра ро стоп ПП стоп стоп стоп стоп стоп
what kind of Russia if in the 10th century there
какой России если в X веке никакой
was no Russia at the time of Julian the
России не было во времена Юлиана
Hungarian Nika Russia PP Russia then
венгерской Никой России ПП России тогда
I read the translation auto translation which is already
я перевод читаю автоперевод который уже
some kind of translation not like that because you
какой-то перевод не такой потому что
don't see Russia what's the matter well send
России не видите в чём дело ну скиньте
me a link I'll open it too I'll see what
мне ссылочку я открою тоже посмотрю что
you're reading you can't post links here
вы читаете тут ссылки же кидать нельзя
Can I not send you a fine for you
Можно я вас не скину вас штраф на вас
this is for sure you give your word yes
это точно точно вы слово даёте да
here I'll send it now with an auto translator
вот авто переводчиком сейчас
now I'll open it No  be afraid So let's go for now
кину сейчас я открою Не бойся Так давай
Look for what is
пока Ищи что ж там
written there here And where did they understand it
написано вот А где они его понимали
maybe this is another part of his letter
может быть это и другая часть его письма
By the way, Hungarians need to be searched for by the word
Кстати венгры надо искать по слову
Hungarians Hungarians
венгры венгры
[music]
[музыка]
Oh here the king from Great Hungary pagans
О тут короля от Великая Венгрия язычники
Hungarians now I'll try to find the first part
венгры сейчас попробую первую часть
in the affairs of the Hungarians
в делах венгри
received that on the great
полученных что на велико
river maybe by language you need to look somewhere I
реки может по языку надо искать где-то
read this plus look You Speak he
читал плюс смотрите Вы Говори он же
wrote in Latin Yes you look at the translation from
писал на латыне Да вы смотрите перевод с
Latin into Hungarian where Already wrong
латыни на венгерский где Уже неправильно
maybe some like names and so
может некоторые типа названия и так
on and now also modern
дальше а теперь ещё и современного
Hungarian into modern Russian of
венгерского на современный русский
course it will not historically translate the
конечно оно исторически не переведёт
name this let's
название это давайте
not with Yes it's better to mention the monks
ть не с Да так луше упоминают монахи
were sent with the exception of a priest
были посланы с исключением священника
named Otta in whom he travels in for a
имени Отта котором путешествует в за
merchant osko check burning languages ​​Yes, that
торговца оско чек горящ тых языках Да
's why he returned to Hungary with him
поэтому он вернулся в Венгрию вя с собой
several friends who should
несколько друзей которые должны
go with them to preach I'm on
отправиться с ними проповедовать я на
this page I'm on this page No it's
этой страни я на этой страни Нет это
a little earlier that's why a little
немножко раньше это почему немножко
earlier I'm trying to type words that is
раньше я Пробую набирать слова э то есть
this is another link Now I'll throw you this
это другую ссылка Сейчас я вам кину вот
here this
это вот здесь это
But this is what he describes that just
Но это вот он описывает что как раз
some priests there in short went Here
какие-то священники там короче пошли Вот
if I remember correctly
если это я правильно
here in the history of Christian Faith was
вот в истории христианских Вера было
imposed the existence of another Vega from
обложено существование ещё одной Веги из
which seven people waited to find a
которой сем жде вы народом чтобы найти
place of residence because the Earth is not Mot
место проживания поскольку Земля не Моть
inhabitants through many countries stop don't come on
жителей через многие страны стоп не подо
let's do it this way you will not voice everything
давайте давайте так вы не озвучу всё
in a row all the letters you Find where Well you
подряд все буквы вы Найдите где Ну вы же
say that they understood him in this in
говорите что его понимали в этом в
Mordovia there well not him more precisely the above
Мордовии там ну не его вернее выше
mentioned monks who were
упомянутые монахи которые были
sent Well this is literally the first first
посланы Ну это вот буквально первая
there look at the title then pretend to be a
первые там заглавие посмотрите тогда
merchant he went into
выдавай себе за торговца он зашёл в
one pagan country several people
одной языческой стране несколько человек
speaking these languages ​​through whom
говорящих на этих языках через которых
both he learned and live here again you
оба он узнал и живут вот ещё раз вы
said Well why was I surprised Yes that they
сказали Ну почему я и удивился Да что
understood him in Hungarian not him they understood but
его понимали на венг не его понимали а
he In short went roughly speaking I don't remember
он Короче пошёл грубо говоря я не помню
somewhere He also about again I Why was I
где-то Он тоже про ещё раз я Почему
surprised and why did I remember about Khanty-
удивился и почему вспомнил про Ханты
Mansi Yes because you said that in
манси Да потому что вы сказали что его в
this Mordovia so further he was understood without
этом мордови так дальше его понимали без
problems and in somewhere  He wrote about this where they
проблем а в где-то Он про это писал где
understood Well, this can't be, I'm
понимали Ну это же не может быть я же
telling you right away, these are such different languages ​​But
Сразу говорю это настолько разные языки
they listened to him very attentively,
А вот они слушали его очень внимательно
as the language was entirely in Hungarian They
как язык был полностью в венгерском Они
understood him and he understood them Stop Stop Stop
понимали его и он понимал их стоп стоп
Where is this, this is number four and
стоп где это вот это номер четыре и
he found them They took them away This is some
нашёл он их увели это ещё какая-то
other page Let's throw it down No, this is the
другая страница давайте скине Нет это
same but he also found them at Veliko Retil
это же но и нашёл он их у велико ретил
No, here's the second one On the second page
нет вот второй во второй странице
that you threw down there's no such thing where number
который вы скинули нету тако где номер
four is written Here are four Here is what
четыре написано вот четыре вот какой
number four you gave me The first page Julis
номер четыре вы мне первая страни джулис
01 dnu 01 The second or yes, the second link
01 дну 01 вторая или да вторая ссылочка
Here I translated it into Russian
вот я перел на русский язык
So it was entirely Hungarian They
так был полностью венгерским Они
understood him and he understood
понимали его и он понимал
them Pagans who don't know God but don't
их язычники которые не знают бога но не
worship The fourth one So
поклоняются четвёртый так
listen So who is
слуша так
he talking about He's not talking
это он про кого рассказывает это он не
about himself About the Hungarians He
про себя про венгров он
found No, it's written and he found them Here you
нашл не ну написано и нашл он их тут
see what the problem is that there were
видите в чём проблема в том что там было
two letters He sent one letter I
два письма одно он послал письмо я так
understand that someone took it for him In short, the
понимаю кто-то за него отнёс короче
letter And the second one he sent himself
письму а второе он уже сам
once again I clearly see that this is
посл ещ раз я чётко вижу что это от
written in the third person Yes and I found about them there is
третьего лица пишет Да и нашл о их есть
this is not about himself not about himself
это не про себян не про себя
he went together or in the second I don’t remember
он пошл вдвоём или втором не помню
how many of them were there Here is one letter of
сколько их там было Вот и одно письмо из
which one letter he took it back
которых одно письмо отнёс его обратно
Here again once again let’s say who is the
Вот ещё раз ещё раз давайте так кто
author Yes that Julian Hungarian but he
автор Да того что Юлиан венгерский но он
asked one person who was with him to
просил одного человека который был с ним
go like home to Hungary I give you a letter There you will pass it on to
идти типа домой в Венгрию даю письмо Там
dad Well, he just
передашь папе Да ну он просто
passed it on Well, and he passed it on then he what
переда Да ну а передавал то он то что
as if heard what he saw stop stop
как бы услышал то что увидел стоп стоп
PP once again once again then Let’s say once again he
ПП ещё раз ещё раз то Давайте ещё раз он
just passed on the letter Or that person
просто передал письмо Или тот человек
conveyed
передал своими словами слова
Julian’s words in his own words Well, I don’t know how it was
Юлиана своими Ну я не знаю как это было
whether he conveyed them in his own words I don’t mean that
передавал ли он своими словами Я же не
Let’s say so from that Well, you and I seem to be
то есть Давайте так из того Ну мы с вами
adults who know the Russian language
вроде взрослые люди знаем русский язык
we understand that this phrase was not written on
мы понимаем что эта фраза написана не от
behalf of Julian Hungarian good Yes it was not
лица Юлиана венгерского хороо Да не от
written on behalf of Julian but all the same as if there
лица Юлиана написано но всё равно как бы
was a person with him who A at his
с ним был человек который А по его
request passed on the letter this in short
просьбе передавал письмо этого короче
Who is the author of this phrase and about  who is he
Кто автор вот этой фразы и про кого он
writing he is writing about the Hungarians whom he
пишет он пишет про венгров которых он
found he is the Great Ve and he found them By the
нашл он же Великую ве и нашл он их У
great river Who is this who found them By the
великой реки Кто этот кто нашл их У
great
великой
river Julian then brother
реки Юлиан тогда брат
Julian stop so it is not
Юлиан стоп значит это пишет не
Julian who is writing it perhaps Well there was a man with him who
Юлиан возможно Ну с ним был человек кото
once let's do it like we are history Iri
е раз давайте так мы как истори Ири
wrote Hungarian Yes he wrote I met
писал венгерски Да он написал я встретил
Hungarians and I can I am Hungarian I met
венгров и я могу я венгр я встретил
Hungarians Here they
венгров Вот они
say it is written by some other
говорят это пишет какой-то другой
person probably not even a
человек походу даже не
Hungarian Hungarian who You don't even know who
венгр венгр кто Вы же даже не знаете кто
it is now I will say he has there about the
это сейчас скажу у него там есть про
description of his journey there who is it
описание его путешествия там кто это вот
in this link who is writing the description of the
в этой ссылке кто же это пишет описание
journey of flax the journey of
путешествия льна путешествие
Julian the
Юлиана
Hungarian someone he sent there I do
венгерского кого-то он там посылал Я уж
n't
не
remember so let's even read Wikipedia the
помню так вот даже Википедии почитаем
first
первое
journey let's do the second letter what is it
путешествие давай так второ письмо как
called this is a report on the first
называется это отчёт о первом
journey of Julian in
путешествии Юлиана
197 yes that is it was not Julian who
197 года да то есть это писал не Юлиан
wrote it some completely leftist
это писал какой-то вообще левый
he walked with him that is Budapest
он с ним походил то есть Будапеште
having passed the rest of Juliana  Gerard Gerard
пройдя оставшийся Юлианы Герард
That's his name Gerard As far as I
Герард Вот его звали Герард Насколько я
understood, Gerard was also
понял то Герард тоже был
Hungarian, it's
венг тут
written here I thought So that means if
написано Я подумал Так значит если бы
Gerard was Hungarian and he met
Герард был венграм и он встретил вместе
these people together with Lin who said they
с лином этих людей которые говорили
understood him, he also said on his own behalf
понимали егон также сказа от себя
I talked to these people, he would have
написал я общался с этими людьми он бы
written on his own behalf I talked to e Sorry,
от себя написал я общался с э Извините
I need to put the child to sleep, put to sleep, why, why
мне надо ребёнка эти усыплять усыплять
put the child to sleep, don't put him to
зачем зачем усыплять ребёнка не усыплять
sleep Let him live a little longer, he
Пусть поживёт
wrote, don't come Save me, otherwise I was
ещё написал же не приди Спаси меня а то
here from
меня тут от
Winger, it was
Вингер это было
divine, damn, such and such, I also
божественно блин такой такой я ему тоже
started to invent some for him, Mustafa
начал придумывать каких-то та Мустафа
Hasansky, there's still more, then Okay, come on Well, there are
Хасанский там ещё ещё ещё потом Ладно
such things Well, they couldn't
давай Ну есть такие вещи Ну не могли его
understand him there, they couldn't already, come on, in short,
там понимать не могли уже давай короче
Okay, like, subscribe, comment, see how
Хорошо лайк подписка комент видите как
he spoke, Vok, Vetas, ran away from him, and I
он говорил Вок ветас убежал от него а я
destroyed him, I'm cooler than KS, Vetas, Bo Vok, he takes
его развалил я круче чем КС ветас бо вок
them too seriously Let's
слишком серьёзно к ним относится Давайте
like, squeak, comment, write on y, Telegram,
лайк писка комент пись на й Telegram
right now, axis VN,
прям зараз ось ВН а
Popik, tse  very and very important YouTube is
Попик це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube
busy with us through the scarg Orcs in your ban and
заня нас через скарг Орки в твый бан и
very many videos are not shown to people
дуже багато видео не показуе людям
at times do not show information about streams so that
вчасно не показуе информация про стримы
we Mali operational
тому для того щоб мы Мали оперативный
links are written right now and
звязок пишиться прямо зараз а
Popik there in telegrams will find videos also
Попик там в телеграми окрим видео ще теж
interesting and useful information and we will oblige
цикава и корисна информация и мы повинни
you to keep constant operational
з вами тримати постийний оперативный
links
звязок
independently in order to show you about this
незалежно в того чи покаже вам про це
YouTube Glory to Ukraine
YouTube Слава Украине
letter a
пись а